Guide to the Montana Department of Transportation, Maintenance Division records 1927-2001
Montana Historical Society
Montana Department of Transportation, Maintenance Division records
1927-2001
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 407
Montana. Department of Transportation.
8.8 linear feet
This collection is comprised of records documenting the work of the Department of Transportation and Department of Highways Maintenance Division and includes correspondence, "complaint" files, flood files, historical markers files, signing and landmark files, inspector field journals, meeting minutes, and subject files. Topics include: the statewide installation of fiber-optic cable through “Touch America” and AT&T, the Kootenai Hydroelectric Facility Project, and aerial photographs of Seeley-Swan Highway.
The Montana State Highway Commission was created in 1913 by the state Legislative Assembly. The original Commission was composed of three members. In 1917 new legislation altered the organization of the Commission by authorizing the appointment of twelve members according to geographic highway districts. Membership was changed again in 1921 to three members appointed by the Governor and in 1941 to five members, also appointed by the Governor. In 1971 the Commission was renamed the Montana Department of Highways, created by Chapter 7 of the Executive Reorganization Act of 1971 and implemented by executive order of the Governor on December 16, 1971. The Department of Highways took over all but the advisory functions of the State Highway Commission.
By 1972, the Department consisted of seven divisions: the Legal Division, Personnel Division, Centralized Services Division, Engineering Division, Motor Pool Division, Gross Vehicle Weight Division, and the Maintenance Division. Each division was headed by an administrator. The Centralized Services Division, Engineering Division, Motor Pool Division, Gross Vehicle Weight Division, and the Maintenance Division were furthered sub-divided into bureaus, headed by Chiefs. In 1991, the Department of Highways became the Department of Transportation.
The Maintenance Division oversaw general maintenance throughout the entire Department of Highways/Transportation including flood mitigation and damage repair, installing and maintaining road signs and Montana’s recognized Historical Highway Markers, managing public complaints about road conditions, as well as other maintenance-related projects. The Maintenance Division also worked closely with the district offices, overseeing the districts’ maintenance projects.
The collection contains files for the Maintenance division as it existed under the Department of Highways and then as part of the Department of Transportation.
The records for the Department of Highways consist of Subject Files (1927-1991) and Correspondence. Correspondence includes general correspondence of the Governor (1978-1985), and of the Maintenance Division Administrator and Engineer (1970-1985). Also included are files regarding the district and area offices (1953-1991), including: correspondence; "complaint" files; flood files; historical markers files; signing and landmark files; and miscellaneous report and project files, including Kootenai Hydroelectric Facility Project and aerial photographs of Seeley-Swan Highway.
The records for the Department of Transportation are comprised entirely of records documenting the Maintenance Division’s work with Power Engineers and “Touch America”/AT&T to install fiber optic cable in Montana. Documents include field diaries, both bound and loose leaf, written by inspectors and project managers overseeing the project; environmental reports and mitigation plans written by Power Engineers, one of the companies contracted to work on the project; general subject files about the project; and meeting minutes.
This collection is organized into two subgroups: (Subgroup 1) Department of Highways, Maintenance Division and (Subgroup 2) Department of Transportation, Maintenance Division. The two subgroups are further organized into series. Subgroup 1 is organized into the series Subject Files and Correspondence. Both Series are arranged alphabetically. Subgroup 2 is organized into the series Diaries, Minutes, Reports, and Subject Files.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Highways.; Transportation--Montana.; Highways--Montana.; Highway engineering--Montana.; Roads--Design and construction--Montana.; Highways--Flood Damage--Montana
Helena (Mont.)--Politics and government
Montana; Transportation
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Montana Department of Highways, Maintenance Division
  - Subject Files
    - Air Field Maintenance, Army Auxiliary, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Civil Aeronautics Administration / Flight Strip Maintenance, 1942-1957 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Craft Council / AFSCME, 1973-1986, 1984 (Box-folder 1/3-6)
    - Disasters / Emergency – Planning, Response, Correspondence, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Division 4 / Froid Case / Highway 16, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Projects: ERF 1-ERF 7, 1948 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Projects: ERF 9-ERF 16, 1948-1949 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Projects: Flood Damage, 1948-1953 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Projects / 1981 Flood Report (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Federal Highway Administration Projects, 1977-1987 (Box-folder 1/13-25)
    - Environmental and Pollution Studies, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 2/1-3)
    - Inactive Radar Bases, 1952-1964 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Interstate Highway System, 1958-1973 (Box-folder 2/5-7)
    - Legislation Affecting Highway, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Letters Prepared for Governor, 1978-1985 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Local Area Road Logs: Maintained by State, undated (Box-folder 2/10-11)
    - Maintenance Division Questionnaires, 1970-1983 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Roadside Camps and Campgrounds, 1935-1968 (Box-folder 2/13-16)
    - Research Committee, 1976-1989 (Box-folder 2/17-19)
    - Reorganization, 1970-1982 (Box-folder 2/20-21)
    - Roadside Parks and Camps, 1936-1971 (Box-folder 2/22)
    - Signs and Signage, 1952-1959 (Box-folder 2/23)
    - Sign and Sign Committee, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 3)
    - Sign and Sign Committee, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 4/1-5)
    - Signals, 1950-1979 (Box-folder 4/6-7)
    - Signals / Crossings, 1955-1976 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Signing / Secondary Roads, 1950-1960 (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Transportation / Maintenance Research, 1973-1978 (Box-folder 4/10)
    - Transportation Research, 1979-1984 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Correspondence
    - Billings District, general, 1972-1991 (Box-folder 4/12-19)
    - Billings District, District Engineer, 1983-1991 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - Billings District, 1978 Flood Damage Photos, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - Billings District, 1978 Flood, 1978-1982 (Box-folder 5/1-2)
    - Billings District, Historical Markers, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Billings District, Legal, 1976-1986 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Bozeman District, general, 1962-1987 (Box-folder 5/5-13)
    - Bozeman District, complaints, 1975-1985 (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Bozeman District, Maintenance Chief, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Butte District, general, 1969-1989 (Box-folder 5/16-23)
    - Butte District, complaints, 1972-1985 (Box-folder 5/24)
    - Butte District, District Engineer, 1982-1986, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 5/25-26)
    - Butte District, Historical Markers, 1970 (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Butte District, Maintenance Chief, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - May 1981 Flood, Newspaper Articles (Box-folder 6/3)
    - May 1981 Flood, Pictures (Box-folder 6/4)
    - Glendive District, general, 1963-1991 (Box-folder 6/5-9)
    - Glendive District, Historical Markers, 1970 (Box-folder 6/10)
    - Great Falls District, general, 1962-1990 (Box-folder 6/11-17)
    - Great Falls District, District Engineer, 1984-1991 (Box-folder 6/18)
    - Great Falls District, Historical Markers, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 6/19)
    - Havre District, general, 1960-1981 (Box-folder 6/20-23)
    - Havre District, Correspondence - “General File”, 1979-1991 (Box-folder 7/1-2)
    - Havre District, Complaint, 1977-1984 (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Havre District, Historical Markers, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Kalispell District, general, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 7/5-6)
    - Kalispell District, Maintenance Chief, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Kalispell District, Floods, 1983 (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Kalispell District, Historic Markers, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Kalispell District, Kootenai Falls Hydroelectric Facility, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Kalispell, Signing and Landmarks, 1969-1986 (Box-folder 7/11)
    - Kalispell District, Signing, 1969-1986 (Box-folder 7/12)
    - Lewistown District, general, 1968-1990 (Box-folder 7/13-17)
    - Lewistown District, Flood Damage, 1970-1983 (Box-folder 7/18)
    - Lewistown District, Historic Markers, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 7/19)
    - Lewistown District, Judith Basin Signing and Historic, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 7/20)
    - Lewistown District, Maintenance Chief, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 7/21)
    - Miles City District, general, 1968-1990 (Box-folder 7/22-28)
    - Miles City District, Floods, 1979-1986 (Box-folder 7/29)
    - Miles City District, Historical Markers, 1970-1985 (Box-folder 7/30)
    - Miles City District, Signing and Landmarks, 1977-1987 (Box-folder 7/31)
    - Missoula District, general, 1959-1975 (Box-folder 7/32)
    - Missoula District, general, 1960-1991 (Box-folder 8/1-6)
    - Missoula District, District Engineer, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Missoula District, Field Review, 1982 January (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Missoula District, Historical Markers, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Missoula District, Seeley-Swan Trees Photographs, 1988 (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Missoula District, Signing and Landmarks, 1971-1989 (Box-folder 8/11-12)
    - Missoula District, Skakhalo Road, 1975 (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Missoula District, Landslide Maintenance, 1975-1990 (Box-folder 8/14)
    - Wolf Point District, general, 1962-1991 (Box-folder 8/15-18)
    - Wolf Point District, Maintenance Chief, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 8/19)
    - Wolf Point District, Floods, 1976-1987 (Box-folder 8/20)
    - Wolf Point District, Historical Markers, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 8/21)
    - Wolf Point District, Signing and Landmarks, 1975-1983 (Box-folder 8/22)
- Montana Department of Transportation, Maintenance Division
  - Diaries
    - Tom Andrus, Inspector, 2001 June–August (Volume Volume 1)
    - Larry Rickard, Inspector, 2001 January–May (Volume Volume 2)
    - Larry Rickard, Inspector, 2001 Febrauary–July (Volume Volume 3)
    - Field Diary: “Touch America” Fiber Optic Cable Installation (B. Berthelson), 2001 January–June (Box-folder 9/1)
    - Field Diary: “Touch America” Fiber Optic Cable Installation Field Diary: “Touch America” Fiber Optic Cable Installation (B. Berthelson), 2001 January–June (Box-folder 9/2)
    - Field Diary: “Touch America” Fiber Optic Cable Installation (Miller), 2001 January–June (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Field Diary: “Touch America” Fiber Optic Cable Installation (Tuhy), 2001 May–September (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Minutes
    - Shop Superintendent Meetings, 1999 May, 1999 December (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Reports
    - “Touch America” Fiber Optic Installation: Utility Environ. Checklist (Billings-Yakima), 2000 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - “Touch America” Fiber Optic Installation: Utility Environ. Checklist (Billings-Seattle), 2000 (Box-folder 10/2)
    - “Touch America” Fiber Optic Installation: Biological Assessments (Plants & Wildlife), 2000 (Box-folder 10/3)
    - “Touch America” Fiber Optic Installation: Biological Assessments (Bull Trout & Sensitive Species), 2000 (Box-folder 10/4)
    - “Touch America” Fiber Optic Installation: Power Engineers, “Construction Plan for National Forest Lands”, 2001 (Box-folder 10/5)
    - “Touch America” Fiber Optic Installation: Power Engineers, “Required Construction Mitigation Measures”, 2001 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Subject Files
    - “Touch America,” Environmental Plans and Permits, 2000 (Box-folder 10/7)
    - “Touch America,” General Information, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 10/8)